Today on the podcast, I sat down with Mike Cagney, the founder of Figur. Figur is a company
that went public in September and that has several exciting lines of business,
including a HELOC origination business and a markets division. They also started the
Provenance blockchain, which is the underlying technology for many of its core activities.
It was great to chat with Mike, really like talking about the impact of stablecoins in
the banking sector and some of the issues that are being debated with respect to the
market structure bill and how Figur is thinking about that. I think you'll enjoy this one.
So without further ado, here is my conversation with Mike Cagney of Figur.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures. All of these expressed
by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions and do not reflect the opinions of
Castle Island Ventures. Guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed
in this podcast. You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific
inducement to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an
expression of their personal opinion. This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brought down by Bad Mortgage Investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group, AIG, 85 billion dollars. This is a
different kind of market and the Fed is asleep. The federal government is stepping in to stabilize
Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the two mortgage giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy with a new
round of quantitative easing. You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start
to worry. So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin, Bitcoin.
Mike, thanks for joining us on the podcast today.
Thanks for having me.
I guess congrats are in order. First of all, you went public I think less than a month ago. So was
it on September 11th? So congratulations. What's that been like?
It's been good. Like, I mean, being public is a step in a long process. We're in this for the
long game and we see an enormous amount of value that we're going to be able to create out of the
public blockchain and its application of financial services. But it was an important milestone.
Great for the team's testament to all the work that's gone in, especially given the last four
years of regulatory Edwin that we've had, being able to come out public, not just to make it
through the regulatory process, but have the public markets want to have access to blockchain
businesses, public blockchain businesses. It's great to see and I think super encouraging for
the ecosystem.
When we started to shift from a political and regulatory climate, did you see that
line of sight towards going public? Was that a catalyst for your business?
Yeah. I mean, if you think about last year, 2024, we were trying to go public.
We were down profitable last year and the regulators just made it really, really difficult.
We were a blockchain business. We did a lot of stuff in crypto. We had a lot of infrastructure
around blockchain and crypto. In an effort to try to go public, I split the company in two.
And I said, well, look, I'll take the really heavy blockchain stuff and put it over into figure
markets. And I brought in my canapop to run figure and my guy worked together for a long time.
He was the chief revenue officer at SoFi when I was CEO there.
She became apparent that we weren't going to be able to go by splitting the business.
So what happened in November when the election occurred, we started thinking, well, this has
pretty significant ramifications for the SEC. And that was one of the considerations, but it was also,
is there a public market appetite?
I went to the bankers and I said, hey, does it make sense to recombine the business?
I gave them the story of why we would recombine and the direction that we would take the business.
And they said, yeah, that makes absolute sense. The reality was it was going to be hard to take
them public separate anyway, because there was so much interdependence. Investors don't like being
invested in a public entity when there's a private entity that's critical to the operations. And I
understand that. We said, all right, well, let's go ahead and do this recombination. And we started
talking about retesting the IPO waters. And it was actually one of my investors that came and said,
this is the incredible time we need to do this. And we just got through this massive pain of
separating the business. That was brutal, miserable. And I'm like, all right, it's a sunk cost.
They can't make the decision based on how miserable that experience was. We had to think
about what is best for our shareholders. And it became pretty clear pretty quick that recombining
was best. But in the beginning, when we were working through with the bankers, Goldman was
left on our S1. And Goldman went through and they're like, I really want to tone down the
blockchain stuff. And they really wanted to make it like a fintech 2.0, which SoFi pioneered.
And I'm like, but it's not that. And they're like, yeah, but you need to talk about your loan
origination system. And I'm like, but we give the loan origination system away for free.
We want to talk about the blockchain and the fact that we built a total market on blockchain.
And we're the only ones who have done that. And it creates liquidity and all this hugely
differentiated stuff. And I literally just fought with the bankers for like the first couple of
months. And they're like, don't use the word DeFi. And I'm like, what do you mean? I'm a very
true decentralized blockchain person. There's lots of entities like Coinbase other than base,
which is moderately decentralized. But it's a centralized brokerage exchange. And I'm a
decentralized person. And I don't take custody of anything. And I believe in the true premise of
decentralization and the value that brings through blockchain. I see three value props
of blockchain. There's transactional efficiency, there's liquidity, and there's DeFi from a
financing standpoint. To me, DeFi is the most powerful thing. When you connect sources and
uses of capital, you unlock huge opportunities of rent disintermediation. The whole premise is
we're trying to get the DeFi. DeFi is the promised land here. When we no longer have warehouses with
new Goldman Sachs, it's all on it. And they're like, yeah, you know, that scares people. Don't
talk about that, blah, blah, blah. I mean, well, I'm absolutely going to talk about it. I'm fighting
the whole time. And then the circle goes public. And then they come back to like, hey, Mike,
really think you should emphasize DeFi. Put a little blockchain on it. All the stuff that you're
doing. And I'm like, you're kidding. Oh, okay. You guys are right. Good thing we've got you bankers
here to help us. I love that story. Let's emphasize DeFi. The buy side was there from the very
beginning. What we had with the buy side was a discussion that I think we made very accessible
to them. What we did is we talked through, hey, we use credit to demonstrate two of these three
things. We've demonstrated transactional efficiency, we demonstrated liquidity.
And now what we're trying to do is demonstrate DeFi and the financing side. We launched this
product, democratized prime. That's how we're doing the DeFi approach. But we're also taking
assets to other L1s. I was on a call this morning. We're taking yields, which is our stable coin and
loan participation onto Solana and SWE and other networks as part of what our ambitions are.
We've demonstrated that on the credit side. And what I said is, look, I'm going to do something
very interesting for you, the buy side. I'm going to do a second QC. I'm going to do a second version
of figure. I'm going to try to launch a second QC. And that equity will be peri-pursuit to the
NASDAQ security. Same rights to profit, same governance, same everything. But it's only going
to be on the blockchain. It's not going to be on DTCC. It's not going to trade on the NASDAQ. It's
going to trade on our alternate trading system. And our ATS is unique in that it's an actual deep
IATS. You and I face off directly and transact there. There's no intermediation, no custodial
construct, just bilateral settlement. And I think it's the only ATS that can do that by the way
other people might argue with me on that. And they're like, well, that's great, Mike,
but why would you do that? The NASDAQ works fine. And I said, it does. And so let's be
cognizant about where the value prop is. I think there's some transactional efficiency here.
Just like I cut 150 basis points of costs out of the securitization process. I'll cut some
costs out of this. Like the transfer agent now is just listening to the blockchain. I have
notification. There's some opportunity costs. That's not a huge number. And they're like,
oh, is it liquidity? Are we going to trade this 24-7? And I'm like, well, you can,
but I don't know how valuable that is. A lot of people are touting 24-7. It's so important,
blah, blah, blah. I've been on FTX to lift them out of bankruptcy. And they had a US equity
per business that traded 24-7. And I can tell you if all that mattered was 24-7, that business
would have been flying and it wasn't. And it was sideways. 24-7 isn't actually a real value
prop either. But here's where it's going to matter for you guys. Around D5, you're going to be able
to take that equity and cross-collateralize it and buy Bitcoin. And vice versa. You're going to be
able to use Bitcoin to buy that equity in a way that's fully integrated and seamless. You can't
do that through prime brokerage. You can't do that in your Robinhood because it's segmented out.
But more interesting, today when you guys lend stock out and it goes on special, it's suddenly
yielding 40% because there's a squeeze. You don't get the 40%. Your prime broker is still paying
funds or not funds anymore, silver or whatever you're indexing to. But now you hold the stock.
You control it. You let it out yourself. You set the rate and you get the economic.
And they're like, that sounds really cool. But what if they don't trade in sync? I'm like,
I will set it up where our treasury will swap the NMS security for the blockchain security
one for one. And that way, by definition, how much liquidity there is on the NMS side,
there's the same amount of liquidity on the blockchain side and vice versa.
Whether it's jump or others, I will get them to come in and make market on this and cut across.
And that's when everyone was like, well, what does that mean for DTCC? And I'm like, no, no,
you're not thinking about it the way I'm thinking about it, which is, yeah, there's no DTCC here.
You don't need a registry. DTCC, I think they generate like $2 billion a year of revenue and
they hold about $50 billion of stream capital. That's rent. That's great to release back into
the ecosystem. But it's tiny in the big realm of economics here. The more interesting thing,
and what I think the security is going to demonstrate is, well, you don't need DTCC,
but you also don't trade on the NASDAQ. You trade on a DEX. You and I can take our MetaMask or
Phantom or figure wallets and attach to that DEX trade. Not only is there no centralized exchange,
there's no introducing broker. So we don't need a Robinhood account or Schwab account or whatever.
We just attach to the DEX trade. And it's like, well, if you don't have that introducing broker,
who deals with margin and who deals with stock loan? DeFi. There's no prime brokeraging. Goldman
Prime, which on the sell side, the prime brokerage is the crown jewel of the business. And they
generate a ton of money for these guys. All goes away. That's what this is going to be able to
demonstrate, which is, blockchain has two aspects. There's the disruption of existing financial
infrastructure and there's the greenfield. Equity is clearly a disruption of existing financial
structure. And I think we have a very defined path of how that's going to work. And I was out,
I think we did 150 investor pitches as part of IPO Roadshow. And about a third of the way through,
I started pitching everybody on the buy side and they were like, yes. I'm like, and what I need you
to do is I need you to then say, hey, this is so good. I'm going to go to my other portfolio
companies and say, why don't you have a second CUSIP on the blockchain? Because it's way better
for me for both the margining standpoint and the stock market standpoint. And I have the same
liquidity, I have the same transactional economics. Why don't you do this? And I think we're going to
be able to affect change from within the way we've always done it, which is we go first.
On the other side with credit, that's greenfield. There is no marketplace for credit. We created
that, but we did it with our loans first. Now we have 170 third parties that originate on our
platform and were a small amount of that production, but we had to be the first ones to do it.
My hope is by the end of this year, we'll have demonstrated the full vertical and the defi on
credit and the horizontal expansion into a new asset class being equity, all native on chain,
where we have a greenfield example and a disruption example that indisputably demonstrate
why blockchain is so important, so powerful. I love that. And you've gotten into market
structure in a way that I just love to geek out on. I'd love to get your take on just what
this looks like almost from a regulatory perspective, four or five years from now,
where you have the NMS market, then you have these blockchain venues, whether they're somewhat
decentralized, fully decentralized. The existing buy side firms and the broker dealers, do you see
them having a fiduciary obligation to connect to these venues? How is best bid best offer? How is
that going to work, do you think? So one, this is being hotly contested as part of clarity.
The challenge we have with clarity is with Genius Act, there was a lot of momentum and a lot of
political reason why no one wanted to stand in front of that. And it went through pretty quickly.
Now the banks all feel they got bamboozled on it because post execution, they realized Coinbase is
paying interest on USDC balances. Since it's not circle paying interest, it satisfies the Genius
Act, but you're still getting interest on Coin, which is what the banks are trying to avoid.
With clarity, you're in a much different situation where you've got the centralized exchanges that
have a very different perspective to the decentralized folks like myself. I care a lot about how do you
deal with a transfer agent in DeFi? And to me, those are things that are super important. Well,
a centralized exchange doesn't care about that. And then you have the existing players like ICE
and NASDAQ, DTCC that are like, well, how do we take the system we have and apply it to the crypto
or blockchain assets? And I view as lipstick on the pig in terms of that process because the
benefit here is to rip everything and start over. The challenge from the regulatory standpoint in
best acts is a big issue. DTCC have this view of, hey, we're going to be able to take a DTCC
security, we're going to vault it and we're going to sell a security entitlement to it.
And that security entitlement can be used in DeFi, it can be a blah, blah, blah, blah.
When they told me this, we were at a dinner when they were talking about this. And I'm like,
there's no way you can do this, at least not under the current regulatory structure.
Sure enough, after they explained this to me, Commissioner Purse did that memo that said,
by the way, a security entitlement of an MS security is still an MS security,
it's still subbing best acts. The issue with best execution is you basically have to direct
to best bid best offer, at least for a portion of the transaction. It's unfortunate because
NMS is sort of classic, the road to hell is paved with good intentions. It actually is not a good
thing for people in my view. But the reason was it was there to prevent you from being gouged by
your broker, sending it to off market exchanges and so forth. It's actually created a huge market
for order flow and other things that aren't necessarily created to consumer market participants.
But the issue is you have to be able to route to best execution. So, a blockchain exchange where
you and I are both encumbering the asset and bilaterally transaction, that's the whole
definition of blockchain exchange or decentralized exchange. We don't take on a part of your
settlement risk, but that means when I lift your offer or you hit my bid, we swap those assets.
We do not then go and look at cross 12 other pools of liquidity as to where we're going to route the
trade. A blockchain native ecosystem won't work in an NMS construct. This is a gap that I think
a lot of people in the space are just getting their arms around and realizing because I think
some of the brokerage firms are like, oh, we're going to send up our own blockchain and we're
going to trade securities on it. We're going to be able to trade Tesla and Intel and Coinbase,
whatever. No, you're not because those are NMS securities. This is why when I talk about what
I'm trying to do, I have to do it as a second Q-Serve because it can't be the same security.
I can't take the NASDAQ security and put it on the blockchain because that's an NMS security,
no matter how I do it. So, it has to be a different security that doesn't touch a
national market exchange. Then you have the ability to create a blockchain native ecosystem
where you can transact bilaterally and sell several self-clear. And the key is to keep that locked in.
There's a convertibility aspect that you can do at the treasury side to swap that security.
Now, there's a bunch of Reg M considerations, other regulatory considerations you have to have
as part of this. So, it's not trivial at all, but it's doable. That's kind of what I'm trying to lean
in on. Yeah, that's fascinating. And you brought up the clarity bill. I mean, how do you handicap
that getting through at this point? This is one of many issues that people are debating. It just
seems a lot more complicated than the stablecoin bill. There's sort of two aspects to it, which is
what is the immediacy of it in terms of its value to the ecosystem? I think Chairman Atkins has been
very clear that, for example, they don't view DeFi as being under SEC purview. There's a question of
how do we define DeFi? Is DeFi decentralized custody or is it all logic on smart contracts?
Is it governance of the market system, et cetera, et cetera? And so, in the near term, I don't know
that it's as important to all of us because I think the SEC, the first thing they did that was
huge is they said, we're not using enforcement as a policy tool. And that allowed lots of us to be
able to wake up in the morning without fear of an arrest warrant being out there or the Friday
afternoon Wells notices or all the things that were happening, give us some degree of comfort.
They've enacted a set of policies or announced a set of intentions that have given a pretty
clear indication to the industry what you can do and what you can't do. The problem is it's not
codified in the law. So, just as this is interpretive to the current chairperson,
another chairperson coming in, they go back to the way it was before. I think we have a longer
runway with clarity. It's not that we have to get it done this year or the industry is going to suffer.
We've got to get it done in the next two and a half to three years or we're going to introduce
a huge amount of uncertainty as to our businesses function against election cycles. That's not a
good thing. No, it's definitely what we want to avoid. You brought up that dinner we were at and
you had some really interesting comments around the banking sector and how certain folks in the
banking sector are really freaking out about deposit flight with stable coins. How do you
think about this? And maybe I'll ask a follow-up question just around what would you be doing if
you're a bank right now? I've spoken to a bunch of bank CEOs about this. The reality is I think if
you're a regional or a super regional bank, your liabilities are going to come under attack and
you're going to lose a lot of them. There are some bank CEOs that say, oh, the government will never
let that happen. We're going to go with community banking or blah, blah, blah, blah. I don't know
if you understand this administration, the populist band of this administration, which is around
Main Street, not bailing banks out or allowing banks to have these enterprise franchise models
that they always underpaid on FDIC insurance historically. And I think there's a recognition
of that in the administration. You're going to be under attack. What do you do when that happens?
Part of what we're doing and going out and doing a road show and that we're meeting a bunch of
these banks and we're saying, hey, look, there's three things we want to talk to you about. One is
this macro event of stable coins. Treasury did a study that says if interest was paid on these
coins, 6.6 trillion would leave the bank liability side, not just retail, but business deposits as
well. I agree with that 100%. I think that that's very correct. And I think it's inevitable.
You already have interest being paid on this indirectly. And because of that,
you will just get to direct interest in the not so distant future. And so that deposit
flight is going to occur. What do you do? Part of what we're saying is, hey, look, we can show you
how to originate assets on blockchain, how to create liquidity and marketplaces on blockchain,
and then how to use DeFi to finance those assets. The paradox of this is the money financing those
assets in DeFi used to be in the bank deposit. You and I taking our deposits out, now putting it
in yielding coin, and then making the decision that, hey, rather than SOFR, we want to make
6% or 7% or 8% on a DeFi marketplace lending against loans on an over collateralized basis.
We're just reallocating those liabilities away from the centralized bank capital allocator to
the decentralized people allocator, where we all make the decision of allocating to finance those
assets. But that capital needs to get tapped. And we saw this and the banks got to preview this
at the end of 22. When the Fed started to tighten, bank deposits went from 18.2 trillion to 17.2
trillion. And the banks at a miserable time, they were selling assets on a prior sale basis,
trying to get everything off the balance sheet. This is a trillion dollars of liabilities.
So 2 trillion goes or 6.6 trillion, which is the treasury study for interest burning goes,
what's going to happen? Well, absent a solution, you have a financial calamity.
Government's not going to let a financial calamity happen. Regulatory step in,
the Fed could do like extending health type structures to create leverage and liquidity
for private capital to step into the bank balance sheet void. It's not enough on its own.
Again, the reality is that 6.6 trillion isn't all going to sit in treasuries. You and I aren't going
to be content with a 4% yield when we can allocate directly on an over collateralized basis and get
seven or eight or whatever it is. The big thing that we're showing the banks is,
here's a roadmap to do this. Now, the second thing that we're talking to them about is,
and by the way, JP is going to take your deposits. JP coin is going to come and they're going to be
able to outcompete you. And some of these regional banks, I think are a little bit delusional. They're
like, oh, no, no, we're going to be able to have XYZ coin and be competitive. And I'm like, you're
not. This is why you can't win and chase bottom rewards. You just can't. They're not going to
beat them in this fight. Why don't we give you our yielding stable coin? We have a coin called
yields and it's actually a security. So it's not subject to the genius act. So it can pay interest.
Why don't we give you the yielding coin? By the way, we can hold in treasuries or bank deposits.
Your customer puts a dollar into yields. We'll hold it on your balance sheet as liability. You've
got to pay interest on it. It's not a free deposit anymore, but you don't have all the costs that you
had of managing that deposit. Historically, you get efficiencies that come off of that.
That gives you a defensive position because now you have an explicit yielding coin whereas JP and
the genius act doesn't. The deposit is staying with you. The customer relationship is staying
with you. The economic scrape is staying with you. But you have to be cognizant of you're either going
to have a higher cost deposit or it's going to be in treasuries. And either way, it's going to have
some impact on your liabilities. And that's why you need this blockchain ecosystem. We're going out
on a roadshow to do this. I joke, the bankers are going to think this is the roadshow of doom
where I should just show up and I'm like, everything in your world is over. But it's not.
I'm saying if you lean in and embrace this technology, you can actually gain a lot of
market share from your competitors who have their heads in the sand and are like, this will never
happen. It must be a fascinating thing to be one of these executive teams that's actually zoned in
on the problem. I get the impression there's quite a few that just aren't aware of it even
yet, which is shocking. But it's not just the liability side of the balance sheet that's
getting chipped away. It's just the asset side is also getting chipped away. If you just look
at the growth of private credit, who's financing buyouts these days, banks getting out of certain
lines of business. So if you almost just do a thought experiment on what it would take
to save the banks from a liability perspective right now, it would be like unlimited FDIC
insurance. And you could actually build stable coins on top of bank deposits within a genius
framework. It's almost like you should be going big and bold with your lobbying efforts.
I think what's interesting is almost all the banks recognize this as an issue and all the
bank boards are talking about it. But some of them do not want to have a discussion about what the
solution is. It is very topical. When we were on our road show at one point, COVID today,
we have a bank that wants to talk about this. Mike, would you be willing to go over and talk
to them? I'm like, sure. And so he comes back, he's like, yeah, they thought you were too
scary. And they didn't want you to talk to them. They wanted somebody else at house. I'm not that
scary. More like a pragmatist in terms of what this is. But we're at a point where this will
go slow and then all at once. But the genie is out of the bottle. With genius, they're not going to
be able to put it back in. And this is the beginning of narrow banking as it affects the
regional banks. It will not be for the money centers because the money centers will actually
benefit because part of the genius act is you can hold treasuries or you can hold bank deposits.
JP will hold bank deposits. And ultimately, the margin in stables will go to zero because
it's a competitive product and people will figure out ways to pay rewards out.
There's homogeneity in the product too. Why is one stable better than the other?
The margin will go to the point where the consumer gets the benefit of the bulk of
the carrier to flow. And then it becomes rewards and application and use cases and other things
that I think banks like Chase are going to dominate. What could have happened is the
government could have taken a more utilitarian approach and said, we're going to create
effectively a uniform payment rail for all coin where no coin can be accepted or denied.
Anything that's conforming as a genius at coin is available for this rail. And here's the
infrastructure. That's not necessarily a capitalistic approach to do it. And why I
don't think they did it that way. There would have been a utility to it. Unlike in the past,
when banks would collude together with things like the Visa network and so forth, I don't think
that's going to happen here. I think the big money centers are going to lean in and say,
you know what? We can just take this market and they're going to try to do it.
I want to rewind the clock a little bit. You were the first person in this industry that really took
a big market. I'm talking about Helox now, infused them with this technology. So what was it that
you originally saw that illuminated the fact that a blockchain could be a good implementation for
this and thorny issues there to figure out around MNPI and just curious how you went around
operationalizing it. The original thesis that we had was we could originate any private credit,
aggregate, securitize it on blockchain and create some savings. That's the first of those three
value props of transaction efficiency. The issue for us, one was MNPI. The issue that we had
when we started was proof of work was still the predominant chain. So Ethereum was still on
proof of work at that point. Bitcoin obviously was a proof of work chain. Proof of stake was coming
to fruition and proof of history with Solana. But the problem with those networks was they function
like a golden data set. So you put a loan on one of those networks, goes out to all the validators.
You now have PI at 100 different anonymous entities you can't control. You can't do that.
We ended up building a blockchain called Provenance that went through a couple of iterations. The
whole premise on Provenance is one of my loans is five gigs of data. I put it on Provenance.
That data goes to an encrypted object store and what goes to the validators is a hash of that data
that they then write such that if I trade a loan with you six months from now, they're going to
reference that data into the encrypted object and you're going to be able to tell whether or not
that was an actual artifact. So it's acting as a data validation agent as a virtual gold data set.
We made Provenance public. We own 20% of the utility token on it called hash. The 80% bulk
of it's in the foundation and there's private parties that hold it and trade it. That was a
necessary condition, but not sufficient. That's what I thought would work and I went to a bunch
of banks. I've told this story lots of times where I'm like, hey, you can do this on blockchain.
We'd like to be the 10th bank to do this. That's when we said, all right, we'll do it ourselves.
In doing it ourselves, we had to be very cognizant of we want to fight it out with rocket on first
lien mortgage or SoFi on personal loans while we're trying to convince the market to use
blockchain. It's not going to work. We had to find, again, the greenest field we could play in on
credit where we think we could originate a valuable asset and not have to compete with anyone to do it.
That's why we chose HemiCredit. It's a mortgage and it is a mortgage asset, but it's one that
hasn't been done well and hasn't been used well. Product market fit historically has been poor for
it. It's a great substitute for personal loans, for example. What we were able to do is bring the
personal loan experience, so a couple minute application process, your money in a couple days
into something that historically took 45 days to get, but was a better product downstream.
What a lot of people don't understand, and when we think about moats and competitive moats,
what we had to do in the beginning is leave a lot of money on the table.
Notably, in the beginning, people would come to us and say, I'll buy your loan. I don't want to
buy it on blockchain. Pay you more if you don't make me buy it on blockchain. My capital market
people were like, can you just sell them $50 million not on blockchain and the rest can be
on blockchain? I'm like, no, absolutely not. We left a lot of money on the table. Then we had
people come to us and say, hey, I don't like your credit box. If you originate to my credit box,
I'll pay one, two, three points more for the loans. Same situation. You do that and then you
don't have ubiquity of the asset and liquidity that you can create off of that ubiquity.
The reality is most entities don't have the ability to leave that money on the table.
If you're a mortgage company, you run razor-thin margins and you take the money when it's there.
If you're a startup, that requires a decent amount of capital and persistence and patient
investors where they're like, well, why don't you just be FinTech 2.0? Because we're building
FinTech 3.0. They had that experience on multiple fronts early on. My board giving me crap about,
well, this online lender is doing better than you, blah, blah. I was like, well,
because I'm building into something bigger. Then I got all kinds of grief about, well,
BlockFi and FTX are doing better than you. I was like, well, because I'm not trying to do
what they're trying to do. Ultimately, the long game won. I think that's what we've always
persisted and why we've been very particular on the private capital side and trying to do so on
the public capital side as well is get investors that buy into that long-term vision because
there's a lot of distractions and diversions that come up on the road that seem like near-term
better opportunity, but take you away from that long-term objective of building real value.
That makes total sense. On the markets business, just talking about the long-term here,
you don't have to squint too hard to see that this technology and people building things on
top of it like yourselves could be a real competitive disruption to CME and some of these
bigger shops. How do you think about that and just competing against some of these incumbents and
what their reaction function will look like? I've never shied away from competing against
entrenched interests. When we started SoFi, obviously, we were pushing hard against banks
in general, and I think we were very successful building our business off of that. I think we
figure it's even broader. It's not just the banks per se. In fact, the banks are more partners with
us, a good figure than competitors, but a lot of the market structure. I think that's been one of
the challenges with blockchain in that generally innovation happens marginal first order. DTCC
figures out a way to get from T plus one to T plus zero as we've gotten from T plus three to two
to one. What blockchain's doing is basically just blowing everything up and doing it in a completely
different way. Blowing it up means that their model doesn't work anymore. There is no marginal
innovation. I always joke about this when I see like visas running stablecoin experiments. Well,
stablecoin really worked. There wouldn't be a visa network because there's no charge tax.
People don't understand what visas value properly is. It's the management of that charge
tax process and we're stablecoin. It's cash. There is no pullback or redemption. If they really
embraced it, they wouldn't have a model. It'd be a completely different business. To me, that's what
the opportunity is, and it goes back to those factions of interest within clarity. I don't
think that the winning game is to try to promote a centralized ecosystem into blockchain and crypto
assets because I think that the established players are very, very good at that centralized
ecosystem. I don't think that any crypto exchange, for example, can stand up against what NASDAQ and
ICE have built on a prairie pursuit basis. I think what you can do is you can do it decentralized
because they'll never do it that way and because their model won't work that way. Decentralization
is better. I can go through the custodians. There was a period of time that Anchorage had this
wonderful moat because they were a regulated entity that tested crypto. While they don't have
the moat in, they're being aggressive. They're trying to work with Tether and others on product
and I commend them for that, but it's a much more competitive dynamic in centralized custody.
Decentralized custody MPC is, in my mind, the better solution, but it doesn't involve any of
those entities, at least in the capacity in which they've always participated. They can still be
node operators on an MPC network. That's not the same as them holding the asset or the economics
from that. I'm not afraid of the entrenched interests because a lot of what we're doing
when you dial it back and look at the true infrastructure is Greenfield. Even the equities
trading that I talked about, it's not that I'm trying to build a better NASDAQ or ICE. I don't
want the centralized exchange. I'm trying to build a DAX to do this. There, there isn't that
competition. Maybe one of the last things I'll ask you is just around provenance. You guys were
really early to this, this concept of getting behind your own chain, birthing it. Stripe's
doing that now. Circle's doing that now. What do you think about that and are we going to see more
of these corporate birthed public blockchains versus the Ethereum style blockchain origins?
One of the things that I've come to terms with, I used to think one blockchain to rule them all.
I don't view that anymore. I think that there's got to be lots of blockchains and requirement of
lots of interoperability. I think that the value proposition of those blockchains will
differ significantly and that some will create value. There's certain idiosyncratic aspects
of provenance that don't exist on networks like Solana or SWE, where there's ways for them to
extract value off of that in terms of people using it. You can just say there's value props
in those other networks too. SWE and Solana are both much faster than provenance. I would argue
none of them are as fast as NASDAQ right now. That's a pragmatic limitation that will be solved.
We will fix that problem. It's technology. It will be fixed. It's just not necessarily relevant
or prevalent today. Five years ago, people were building chains because they're like,
hey, we can issue this token and people will pay a lot of money for it. People were pitching
in these use cases and I'm like, I don't understand why you need a blockchain. Well,
because we can sell the token. I was like, but blockchain is very limiting in what it does,
which is if you do not have a native digital asset on the chain, it's basically workless
technology. Obviously, again, lots of heat from other people in the ecosystem on this and
arguing to me about how valuable oracles are and all this other stuff. But to me,
if you create a new digital asset, the blockchain has a lot of value. If you don't, it doesn't.
A lot of people today are also looking at that in the same way as to, oh, they look at the market
cap of Solana, for example, and they're like, well, wow, we have that. I don't know if things
are going to converge up to the market cap of Solana or things are going to go the other
direction. I don't know if it's the Dapps that live on chain that extract the economics or the
L1 itself. Obviously, if you look at the market cap of MasterCard and Visa, it's over a trillion
dollars. Okay, well, blockchain could displace that. It's not crazy to think a blockchain would
have a trillion dollar market cap because it's displacing that economic structure. But is it the
blockchain or is it the smart contracts and the other applications that are built on top of it
that are extracting that? Or does it all just go back to the ecosystem?
Is it consumer surplus at the end of the day?
That's right. I think we're in the very nascent stages of all this. And so I understand why
everyone wants their own blockchain. I just don't think that it's practical.
Well, Mike, I feel like I get smarter every time I hear you talk. Thanks for coming on.
And where can we send people to learn more about Figure?
You can go to figure.com for figure stuff, figuremarkets.com for the crypto blockchain
stuff, and providence.io for what we're working on with that protocol.
Awesome. Well, congrats on all the success and thanks again for coming on.
Thanks for having me.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island. To learn more
about Castle Island, visit castleisland.vc. And to listen to all of our podcast episodes,
please visit castleisland.vc.com slash podcast, or just click on the tab on our website.
Thanks for listening.